New Caledonia City Clerk fonds
City of New Caledonia Archives
New Caledonia City Clerk fonds
1886-2003, predominant 1886-1993
PR-84
City of New Caledonia. Office of the City Clerk
ca. 320 m of textual records ca. 4,000 photographs 13 videocassettes
City of New Caledonia Archives 1234 Sunshine Street New Caledonia BC V6A 2C3 Canada
The responsibilities of the City Clerk were established with the Act of Incorporation in 1886, which declared the City Clerk to be the Returning Officer of the City (the official responsible for voters' lists and elections). Additional duties included purchasing supplies and were somewhat undefined. With the clarifications of the 1900 Act of Incorporation, formalized responsibilities included recording Council minutes, keeping custody of the by-laws, and maintaining financial records. The Clerk also received all mail directed to the City. A 1912 by-law assigned responsibility for facilitating communication between the citizens, the Mayor, Council, and Council's committees to the City Clerk. In a 1953 Act of Incorporation amendment, the Clerk was named as custodian of the City seal. With the exception of financial functions, which long ago passed to financial officers, the Clerk's responsibilities have remained remarkably consistent. Although the formal organization of the City Clerk's Department has in recent years consisted of a number of divisions - the Council secretariat, the Voters' List Division, periodically a small Public Relations/Communications Division, and the Archives and Records Division (since 1970) - in practice, the Office of the City Clerk has included all divisional sections except the Archives. During some periods the Office of the City Clerk was more commonly referred to as the City Clerk's Office, though the former has prevailed.
Fonds includes the records of City Council of the City of New Caledonia, of the Office of the City Clerk (Council's secretariat), of elections and public relations divisions (both very small, and the elections division in operation only during election periods), and of the numerous committees, boards, and commissions whose records were/are the responsibility of the City Clerk. The fonds does not include the records of the Archives because it operates like a research institution. The series below are listed alphabetically by the creating office. The City's primary governing records are created by Council, under "New Caledonia (B.C.). City Council" (by-laws, Council minutes, etc.), while the supporting documents to City Council records are within the series of the Clerk's, under "New Caledonia (B.C.). Office of the City Clerk". The official records of the various boards are considered to be created by those boards (e.g. Airport Board). Please note that the minutes of standing committees of Council are appended to Council minutes as of 1951.
City of New Caledonia. Office of the City Clerk; Local government
Associated material: Pre-1911 records for the former Carterville Townsite are held at the B.C. Archives. Related records: For South Caledonia and Webster's Corner municipality Council, City Clerk's, and all other retained archival records dating from before amalgamation with the City of New Caledonia in 1929, see the Corporation of the District of South Caledonia fonds and the Corporation of Webster's Corner fonds. The offices forming City Council, the mayor and aldermen (now called councillors), are arranged as the Mayor's Office fonds and the Councillors' office fonds.
Series descriptions and file lists available.
- Subject files - including Council supporting documents, 1886-1976; 62; 102.3 m of textual records ca. 50 photographs 7 maps
  Series consists of administrative and operational files on any matters dealt with by the Office of the City Clerk over time, in its and the individual Clerks' roles as Council secretariat, elections office(r), and information office(r). The scope of City and outside bodies represented, the topics covered, and the types of records contained (primarily correspondence, but also including minutes, contracts, grant applications, etc.) is immense. There is a problem of organization with Office of the City Clerk's files in that, during some periods, files contained here were organized separately (therefore are separate series), while during other periods, those same files were integrated here (e.g. Traffic Commission, Council committees, etc.) Database searching alleviates the problem. Arranged in annual sets (date ranges filed by latest year represented) and therein alphabetically by file title (please note that there is tremendous inconsistency in file title formulation during some periods, see arrangement note below).
  The filing system was not followed consistently with the result that letters on one subject may be found under a variety of headings (for example, letters concerning the British Columbia Sugar Refining Company may be filed under "B" for "British Columbia", "S" for "sugar", or "R" for "B.T. Rogers"). Please note also that every year has files designated "Alphabetical file", which contain correspondence from organizations and individuals who were not assigned a separate subject file (and there is filing inconsistency here as well, i.e. a subject file may exist, yet some items pertaining to that subject ended up in "Alphabetical file").
  Records from 1886-1955 were transferred from the Voters List building, Yukon Street, in 1971 and from the City Clerk's vault and vault no. 2, City Hall, in 1972.
  No further accruals expected.
  Early files (most to 1918) have been microfilmed (MCR 3 and M 107 as indicated on boxes in stacks).
  Series 29 (Outward correspondence, 1886-1975) is the counterpart to this series which was formerly called "Inward correspondence", however, series 29 consists solely of letter press books containing the Clerk's outgoing correspondence and this series contains every other document on a given subject including (variously complete) outward correspondence (once the approximate date of a given subject has been identified from series 20, researchers might wish to consult that period in series 29); this series subdivided after 1974 (as scheduled at that time), therefore continued by series 60 (Housekeeping subject files, selected files only retained by Archives) and series 62 (Operational subject files, all retained).
  Some files less than 100 years old restricted for privacy reasons; please consult the archivist.
  File list available.
  - Proposed development plan for parks: 1959-1976, 1960-1962 (Box Box A12)
  - Standing Committee on Planning and Development - Downtown - parking, 1973-1974 (Box Box A12)
  - Standing Committee on Planning and Development - Downtown - Adams properties (Robson and Alberni), 1974 (Box Box D9, Box Box D10)
  - Standing Committee on Planning and Development - Downtown - transportation, 1974; File consists of 7 maps of proposed transportation routes in downtown New Caledonia. (Mapcabinet C4)
  - Standing Committee on Planning and Development - Downtown - taxi use, 1973 - 1974 (Box Box A12)
  - Standing Committee on Planning and Development - Downtown - Railway Relocation and Crossing Act, 1974 (Box Box A12)
- Correspondence registers, 1935-1972; 104; 1.88 m of textual records
  Series consists of registers of incoming correspondence and interdepartmental mail received by the City Clerk's office. The registers record the date, name of sender, subject of letter, and the individual or department to whom it was forwarded. The registers of incoming correspondence date from 1947 to 1969; the registers of interdepartmental mail date from 1935 to 1972. Arranged chronologically.
  This series is closed. The correspondence registers were discontinued in 1972.
  - Incoming correspondence register, 4 Mar. 1940 - 2 Feb. 1944; 1187
  - Incoming correspondence register, 9 Nov. 1935 - 2 Mar. 1940; 1402